DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宫饭》
It's locked again.
又是锁住的
Give me a minute.
给我一点时间
I'll open it in no time.
我很快就会打开
We walked quite a bit already,
我们走了很长一段距离
so maybe we can call it a day soon.
今天也差不多该休息了
You sure are clever, Marcille, answering with your stomach.
你真厉害 玛露希尔 竟能用肚子回话
It wasn't me!
那不是我肚子的声音啦
It's completely normal.
会那样是正常的
After all, we've only had snacks today.
毕竟我们今天只吃了点心
But Laios, I'm against taking a break.
不过呢 莱欧斯 老夫反对休息
The only foodstuff we found today was a bowl full of Treasure Bugs.
今天找到的食材只有一碗宝物虫
Even if we have to push ourselves, we should make for the fourth floor.
即使多少有点勉强 也应该前进到第四层
Still, the monsters will get tougher and tougher the further we go.
说是这么说 接下来的魔物会越来越难缠
I think we should conserve our energy.
所以想先储备一点体力
But even if we save our energy,
不过要是保留了体力
it won't matter if we pass out from hunger.
结果却因为空腹而倒下就麻烦了
But without energy, we wouldn't be able to defeat monsters…
不过体力耗尽的话 到头来也没办法打倒魔物…
It's open.
打开了
This room looks like it used to be a dining hall.
这房间本来是食堂吧
This must've been a luxurious dining table once upon a time.
以前一定是张豪华的餐桌
But now, it's just the dead haunting this place.
如今只剩死人在这里徘徊
There's not even a single rat in here.
连一只老鼠都没有
I'm not eating a rat, okay?
我可不吃老鼠喔
I wonder why it's always dead humans who attack us.
为什么老是只有死人袭击我们？
Can't a whole roasted pig come after us for a change?
我还比较希望是被一只烤全猪攻击呢
Don't be silly.
说什么傻话？
"Come after us"…
“袭击我们”…
But we do have…
确实存在着其他…
food coming after us!
会袭击我们的食物
Living Painting?
活绘画？
Watch it, Laios!
小心啊 莱欧斯
You got too close!
你靠太近了啦
You could've gotten sucked in!
你想被吸进去吗？
That's what I wanted! I was just getting to the good part!
对啦 刚才正是好时机耶
What?
什么啦？
There were grapes in that painting.
那幅画里有葡萄
In other words,
也就是说
you were trying to eat the food in the painting.
你想吃画里面的食物啊
That's right. Pretty neat idea, don't you think?
没错 不觉得这是个好点子吗？
-Absolutely not! -You moron!
-完全不觉得 -你是笨蛋吗？
-Moron! What were you thinking? -Ever heard the saying, "pie in the sky"?
-蠢蛋 你在想什么啦？ -你听过“画饼充饥”这句话吗？
I-I know you can't actually eat a pie in the sky.
人类的确没办法吃到图画中的饼
But a painting of someone eating a pie in the sky works!
但如果是吃画中之饼的人到画里面 理论就能成立了
You'll end up getting killed inside the painting.
不过你最终只会在画里被杀掉啊
Precisely!
那就是重点
Inside the painting, we should be able to interact with each other!
证明了在画里是能互相干涉的
Fine. Have it your way, then.
知道了啦 那就随你便吧
But you can only give it a try once.
但只能试一次喔
We'll tie a rope around you.
老夫用绳子把你绑起来
If you give us a signal, we'll pull you out.
你打信号我们就会拉你出来
Which painting should I go for?
该选哪幅画才好呢？
This one looks pretty good.
这幅感觉不错喔
There's a lot of delicious food in it.
里面有好多佳肴呢
All right, I'll go for this painting.
好 就选这幅画看看
Ow.
好痛啊
Hey, you.
那边的先生
I've already been spotted!
一进来就被发现了吗？
That sword…
看你的那把剑…
You're wearing odd armor,
虽然你穿的铠甲很奇怪
but you're one of the castle guards, aren't you?
但你是城堡里的侍卫吧？
Huh?
什么？
Here, carry this.
来 帮忙端这个
Seriously, we're always running short on hands.
真是的 人手再多都不够用
This way! Don't space out!
来这边 别发呆了
Look at his face. He looks so clever!
瞧瞧这张脸 看起来聪明伶俐呢
Yes, the shape of his nose is just like yours.
是啊 鼻子的形状长得跟你一模一样
He will lead the kingdom splendidly one day.
总有一天 他将会出色地带领我国
-There, there. You're a good boy. -Congratulations, Your Majesty.
-好乖 你这孩子真乖啊 -弗利纳格陛下 恭喜您
Stop daydreaming!
你别站着发愣了
Bring the next plate already!
快点去端下一盘来
-Um, could I have a bite-- -I have it!
-请问一下 我能吃一口… -好
Delgal! Your name is Delgal!
迪尔加路 你就叫迪尔加路吧
Delgal, you'll become a great king!
迪尔加路 要成为贤明的国王喔
This is no good!
行不通啦
There's no chance of me eating anything!
根本没机会吃
Help me out!
帮帮我吧
It's his signal!
有信号了
Pull!
一起拉
How was it?
怎么样？
I was so close to getting a bite.
只差一点就能吃到了
But the vibe just wasn't right.
但总觉得不是那种气氛
-The vibe? -That's what stopped you?
-气氛？ -问题出在那里吗？
Yeah, it was totally the vibe.
对啊 就是当下的气氛阻止了我
One more time!
再试一次
I can grab a bite if the situation is more suitable.
如果是个更适合的场合就吃得到
What do you mean by "suitable"?
“适合的场合”是什么啦？
Let's see.
我想想
I guess it needs to be more casual.
就是那种能随意大吃大喝的感觉
Casual?
随意大吃大喝？
How about this one?
这幅怎么样？
They have fancy food, it looks like a party,
看起来有很多美食 也像是在庆祝
and there's even someone dancing naked.
还有人光着身体跳舞呢
This is it! Here I go!
就是这个 我出发了
You drunk fool!
你这个蠢醉汉
What do you think you're doing in front of the king?
在国王面前闹哪出？
Get down from the table now!
赶快从桌上下来
Oh, stop it.
算了 住手吧
Today is my wedding day.
毕竟今天是我的婚礼
Pardon this man for getting a little too carried away.
虽然有些逾矩 但就原谅他吧
But Prince Delgal…
但是迪尔加路王子…
Delgal?
迪尔加路？
Is he the baby in the painting earlier?
他是刚才那幅画里的婴儿？
Come on, go!
好了 快走
That was a close call!
得救了
Delgal!
迪尔加路
Father!
父王
I am glad to see how splendidly you have grown.
真高兴看到你成长得如此杰出
To the future of this kingdom.
敬这座王国的未来
F-Father!
父王
He was poisoned!
他被下毒了
Guess I'll take some back with me and enjoy them quietly later.
总之就拿回去慢慢吃吧
Sorry.
不好意思
Your Majesty!
国王陛下
Treat him now!
快替他治疗
Hurry!
动作快
That elf, I spotted him in the previous painting as well.
我在之前那幅画也有看到那名精灵
I wonder if he's a jester or something.
是宫廷小丑之类的吗？
Look what I've got!
你们快看
I brought back food this time…
这次我可是带了食物回来…
Wait, what? It's all gone!
等等 怎么会？什么都没有
So I can't take food out of the painting.
所以食物没办法带到画的外面吗？
The only way is to eat them inside the painting!
没有在画里吃就没有意义
Again! Now that it's come to this, I must have a taste of the food!
换下一幅 都这个地步了 无论如何我都想尝尝味道
FULL-COURSE OF COURT CUISINE
（宫廷料理全餐）
Is this a crowning ceremony?
这是加冕典礼？
So that prince succeeded to the throne.
后来那位王子继承了王位啊
May this kingdom and its people flourish for eternity.
愿这座王国及子民们永世繁荣
It's good!
真美味
I thought it might taste like paint,
本以为会是颜料的味道
but this is a real feast!
但这是真正的美食飨宴啊
Seconds, please.
请再给我一份
I sure ate a ton.
吃得好饱啊
I'm stuffed.
肚子好撑
Guess I'll go back now.
那我该回去了
Huh? This is…
怪了 这位是…
-You don't belong to this castle. -Damn!
-你不是这座城堡里的人吧 -惨了
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
You were there when the prince was born and also at his wedding.
王子诞生那天和婚礼时 你也都在场吧
What is your purpose?
你有什么目的？
Are you after the throne?
你在觊觎王位？
I'll reduce you to ashes right now!
我现在就把你烧成灰烬
The painting!
那幅画
Did something happen inside the painting?
在画里发生什么事了？
There were tons of mouthwatering dishes.
里面摆满了许多山珍海味
As I was about to leave after eating my fill,
当我吃饱喝足 打算回来时
someone realized I was an outsider, grabbed me by the collar,
被某人发现我是外部人士 对方抓住我的衣领
and got really mad.
然后大发雷霆
I'm not surprised.
当然会生气啊
I was so scared.
吓死我了
Now that I'm relaxed, I'm starting to feel hungry again.
松了一口气之后好像又饿了
Wait, what? Even though I ate a lot, my stomach still feels empty!
太奇怪了 我吃了那么多 胃却依然是空的
What did we tell you?
我就说吧
It was just a pie in the sky!
果然是画饼充饥嘛
You wasted our time!
把浪费的时间还来
But it really tasted good!
但真的很好吃啊
Was this the kitchen?
这里是厨房？
We can collect water from the room next door,
我们能从隔壁房间取水
and it's a nice spot to rest for a bit.
这是一个休息的好地方
If you hadn't fooled around with the paintings,
要不是你在画里玩耍
we probably could've reached the fourth floor by now.
我们早就已经走到第四层了
Is that a Mimic?
那不是宝箱怪吗？
I've never noticed that box there before.
我记得此处以前没有那样的箱子
It's not super obvious, but it's not exactly hidden, either.
不会太显眼 也不会太隐密
It's positioned in a way that catches your eye.
会不经意地吸引他人视线的位置
It's in a spot those bastards are fond of.
正是那混帐会喜欢的地方
So, let's get some shut-eye here today.
总之今天就在这里睡觉吧
Okay.
知道了
You good with that, Chilchuck?
可以吗 奇尔查克？
Sure.
可以
I suppose I don't have to tell them.
还是别跟他们说吧
I just know Senshi and Laios will insist on eating it.
反正先西和莱欧斯肯定会吵着要吃
Then, it'll be up to me to open the box.
那样一来我就要负责打开箱子了
Mimics…
宝箱怪…
I've lost count of the times those bastards have caused me misery!
那东西可是害我有多次痛苦的经历
All right!
很好
It doesn't have a lock or a trap!
没上锁 也没陷阱
Since this was locked, it's not a Mimic!
因为这箱子有上锁 所以不是宝箱怪
If I open it from behind, it shouldn't be able to hurt me!
从背后打开就伤不了我了吧
Dammit! I forgot about the trap!
不妙 我忘记有陷阱了
Damn Mimics!
可恶的宝箱怪
You okay?
你没事吧？
You seemed lost in thought.
我看你一直在发呆
Is something bothering you?
是在担心什么吗？
No, not really.
不 没什么
You must be tired.
你一定是累了吧
You're still a child, after all.
毕竟你还只是个孩子
Let him have a good night's sleep without having to stand guard.
今天就别让他守夜了 让他好好睡上一觉
Like I said, I'm not a kid!
都说过我不是小孩了
So, how old are you?
那你几岁？
I'd rather not say.
我不想讲
There you go again. You're always like that.
又来了 奇尔查克老是这样
You won't even tell us your hometown or your birthday.
连出生地和生日都不说
I prefer to keep my job and personal life in separate lanes.
我喜欢把公事跟私事分开
One of these days, you'll miss out if you keep acting that way.
你那样总有一天会吃亏喔
Sure, whatever.
好 随便啦
I've become more sensitive to hunger.
我越来越忍受不了饥饿了
I used to be fine without food for two days.
之前本来两天不吃饭都没问题
I'll go and fetch some water from the next room.
去隔壁装点水吧
Hey, slowpoke.
喂 迟钝女孩
I'm going to draw some water.
我去装点水
I'll go with you.
我跟你一起去
Don't bother. I'll be right back.
不用 我马上回来
It's dangerous.
很危险喔
It's just the next room.
我只是去隔壁而已
A Coin Bug.
是硬币虫
I wonder if there's a nest nearby.
附近有它们的巢穴吗？
If I can find a few more, it might help ease our hunger.
再找几只就能充饥了吧
Not to sound like Laios, but I kinda like Coin Bugs.
虽然不像莱欧斯那么疯狂 但我满喜欢硬币虫的
They're monsters that camouflage like Mimics,
虽然跟宝箱怪一样是拟态的魔物
but they're cute.
但却有可爱之处
Hey!
喂
Wait a minute, that's where the Mimic--
等一下 那边是宝箱怪的…
You idiot.
我这蠢蛋
You forgot you're heavier with the water bag.
竟然忘记加上水袋后会变重
There should be a mechanism nearby to open this door.
附近应该有能打开铁栏杆的机关
Of course, it's out of reach.
远到不可能碰得到
Should I call for help?
要求救吗？
If my yelling attracts more monsters, it will put my friends in danger.
要是其他魔物闻声而来 伙伴们就危险了
Don't worry.
不必担心
If I don't return, Marcille will notice.
我迟迟没回去的话 玛露希尔一定会注意到
Will she? No, she probably won't.
会吗？她大概不会发现吧
I can't count on her!
指望不了她
Don't panic!
别慌张
Opening closed doors
负责打开被关上的门
is your job, isn't it?
不就是你的工作吗？
This type of door opens once you figure out its mechanism.
这种门只要解开机关就能打开
I'll be safe as long as I don't touch the Mimic.
不碰到宝箱怪就没问题
I don't hear any strange device making noise,
没听到有奇怪的装置在运转的声音
so there's no time limit, either.
可推测没有时间限制
There are a couple of buttons on the wall
墙上有几个开关
and a mechanism that likely triggers spears to pop up.
地上的机关看起来会伸出长枪
If I press the buttons in the wrong order, they probably spring up.
按开关的顺序错了就会冒出来吧
And the text on this plate is likely the key, but…
而这块板子上的句子就是关键…
It's in some ancient language, and I can't make heads or tails of it.
这是用古老的语言写上的吧 最好是看得懂啦
Darn it, if only Marcille were around.
可恶 要是玛露希尔在就好了
But it seems strangely familiar…
但总觉得有些熟悉…
Nah, I should get my thoughts in order first.
搞不懂 先整理一下状况吧
There are three buttons in the corners of the room.
房间角落有三个开关
Why three?
为什么是三个？
Do I need to press them in a specific sequence?
要依照某种顺序按下去吗？
There's a button behind the Mimic as well!
宝箱怪的后面也有开关
Darn it! That bastard is set on hindering me at every turn!
可恶 宝箱怪总是处处阻挠我
Could there be a hint inside the room?
房间里有没有什么提示？
Of course not.
怎么可能会有
Even if I press the buttons randomly, I'll only end up getting skewered.
随便按的话只会被刺成一串
But since I'm small, maybe I could dodge them.
我这体型应该能从缝隙穿过
Nah, it's too risky.
不 太危险了
Ugh, I have no idea what to do!
真是够了 完全不知道该怎么做
Maybe I should just stay still until dawn…
我只能老实等到天亮了…
You were in here?!
原来你在这里啊？
Darn--
等…
Ow.
好痛啊
I-I was saved--
我得救…
You sure are tough!
你还真结实
Mimics are cute when you turn them over, and they wiggle their legs.
宝箱怪要是被翻过来 就会在地上挥动脚 很可爱喔
You can tell their sex by turning them over.
让它们翻身就能分出性别了
Laios' useless trivia is coming back to me one after another!
莱欧斯那些没用的小知识 就像跑马灯似地闪现
Turn them over?
让它们翻身？
As if that's possible!
怎么可能做到啊
Here goes nothing!
只能赌一把了
Ow.
真痛
I wonder if they're on their way to help me after all that commotion.
听到刚才那阵骚动后 会不会有人来救我？
Huh?
搞什么？
So this one was empty?
所以这个是空的啊？
How dare you mock me like that!
竟敢耍我
Huh?
什么？
This text…
这文字…
So this is what was written on the plate!
是刚才那块板子上的句子
In that case, I know what it says!
如果是这个 我就知道写的是什么了
Hurry!
动作快
-East! -No matter how many times the sun rises…
-东侧 -“无论太阳东升多少次…”
-West! -And the moon sinks…
-西侧 -“无论月亮西沉多少次…”
-North! -Like the unmoving stars…
-北侧 -“都像在定点不动的星辰般…”
South!
南侧
May the wind of fortune forever blow your way!
“愿能永世沐浴于幸福之风”
It opened!
打开了
Chilchuck isn't coming back!
奇尔查克没有回来
C-Chilchuck!
奇尔查克
I'm sorry, I'm so sorry!
对不起 我很抱歉
I'm alive, okay?
我还活着啦
What's this?
这是什么？
Did you do this, Chilchuck?
这是你弄的吗 奇尔查克？
Well done!
做得好啊
Sure.
感谢夸奖
What a fine Mimic.
这宝箱怪真大只啊
A Mimic, huh?
宝箱怪啊？
It's going to be my first time cooking it.
这还是老夫第一次调理
Don't try to eat it as if it's the normal thing to do!
别理所当然地想吃掉它啊
Don't worry, Marcille.
没事啦 玛露希尔
Mimics on their own aren't poisonous.
宝箱怪本身没有毒性
They can be toxic depending on their diet,
虽然可能会依据 它们吃下的东西变成有毒的
but if you remove their digestive organs, it should be safe.
但把消化器官拿掉就没问题了吧
How is that supposed to be safe?
我倒是听不出哪部分没问题
Forget it, Marcille.
放弃吧 玛露希尔
There's no point in telling them not to.
跟他们说什么都是白费力气
But today, I won't eat it, no matter what!
不过唯独今天 我是绝对不会吃的
Boil plenty of water,
烧开大量的热水
add some salt.
然后加盐
Place the Mimic inside, cover it with a lid,
放入宝箱怪后盖上锅盖
and wait a while.
稍等一会
When it's boiled enough,
充分煮熟后
it's done!
就完成了
BOILED MIMIC
（水煮宝箱怪）
It's hard to scoop out the meat.
很难取出它的肉
How about using the handle instead?
用握柄那端的话呢？
It's no good. I'm only pushing it deeper inside.
还是不行 只会往更深处推
Right.
对了
Chilchuck, let me use those things.
奇尔查克 借一下那个
Those things?
哪个？
You know, the picking tools you're always carrying around.
就是你总是随身带着的开锁工具
Picking tools.
开锁工具
A-Are you out of your mind?
你疯了吗？
It should be fine if we disinfect them in boiling water.
只要煮沸消毒就没问题了
That's not the problem!
不是那个问题
D-Don't!
住手
It's easy to scoop now!
真容易取出来啊
Here.
来
It's really good.
非常好吃
This is really tasty.
这真的美味无比呢
I bet it would be delicious to eat the back meat and leg meat together.
同时吃背部和腿部的肉 味道似乎会很不错呢
It wasn't as good as I thought.
好像也没有
They say the digestive gland of hermit crabs tastes bad.
我听说寄居蟹科的消化腺很难吃
But why didn't you tell us about the Mimic?
但你为什么不告诉我们宝箱怪的事？
I have unpleasant memories associated with Mimics.
宝箱怪给我的回忆没一件是好事
Ideally, I'd like to steer clear of them entirely.
如果能不扯上关系 尽量避开是最好的
Anyway, I've made quite a few errors in judgment.
总之就是各方面的判断都有失误
I panicked thinking it might eat the Treasure Bug.
一想到它要吃掉宝物虫就慌了
Mimics don't eat Treasure Bugs.
宝箱怪不会吃宝物虫喔
What?
什么？
On the contrary, Treasure Bugs feed on Mimics.
反而是宝物虫会吃宝箱怪
When they find a Mimic,
当它们发现宝箱怪
they enter the box through the crack and lay their eggs.
就会在箱子的缝隙间产卵
And the larvae that hatch inside the box grow as they consume the Mimic.
在箱子里孵化的幼虫 会边吃宝箱怪边长大
Once they become adult insects,
等到变成成虫后
they're often confused for treasure by humans,
人类就会误以为那是宝箱
and they take flight to begin their next phase of life.
然后它们便能顺势前往新天地
Are you kidding me?
搞什么嘛
Cut it out, will you?
就叫你停手了
That's what you get for not telling me your age.
谁叫你不告诉我年纪
Didn't you learn that you can miss out when you keep secrets from your friends?
瞒着伙伴是很吃亏的 你应该也学到一课了吧？
Come on, tell me how old you are!
告诉我你现在几岁嘛
Th…
今…
"Th…"?
“今”？
This year, I turn 29.
今年29岁
So you really are a kid. How boring!
原来真的是小孩子 好没意思喔
I didn't know you were so young.
原来你那么年幼啊
Well, why don't you tell me your ages, then!
我才想问你们几岁呢
This is what I hate about long-lived races!
就是因为这样 我才讨厌寿命很长的种族
What?
怎样啦？
Um, Mister… Chilchuck…
那个 奇尔查克先生…
Stop it!
别那样叫我
Today, you feast on a monster,
虽然今天的食材是魔物
but tomorrow, you could end up as someone's meal.
然而到了明天 可能就换作自己被当成食物
Dungeon food.
迷宫饭
Oh, dungeon food.
哦 迷宫饭
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻译：梁雪莹